<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The flight of time, discerned by the dim shadow of Iobs diall, Iob. 9. 25 Explaned in certaine familiar and profitable meditations well conducing to the wise numbering of our daies in the sad time of this mortalitie. As it was delivered to his charge at Bloxham in Oxford-shire by the pastour thereof. R.M.</title>
            <author>Matthew, Roger, b. 1574 or 5.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1634</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07259</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17654A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120930</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856123</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856123</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21645</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07259)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21645)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1387:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The flight of time, discerned by the dim shadow of Iobs diall, Iob. 9. 25 Explaned in certaine familiar and profitable meditations well conducing to the wise numbering of our daies in the sad time of this mortalitie. As it was delivered to his charge at Bloxham in Oxford-shire by the pastour thereof. R.M.</title>
                  <author>Matthew, Roger, b. 1574 or 5.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Miller for Edward Langham at Banbery,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1634.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Roger Matthevv.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>A variant of the edition with George Edwards as publisher in the imprint.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Job --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21645:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21645:1"/>
            <p>THE FLIGHT OF TIME, <hi>Diſcerned</hi> By the dim ſhadow of <hi>Jobs</hi> Diall, IOB 9.25.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Explaned</hi> In certaine familiar and profitable <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations well conducing to the wiſe numbering of our daies in the ſad time of this mortalitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As it was delivered to his charge at <hi>Bloxham</hi> in <hi>Oxford-ſhire</hi> by the Paſtour thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>R. M.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 90.12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Lord, So teach us to number our Dayes, that we may apply our hearts unto wiſdome.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>George Miller,</hi> for <hi>Edward Langham</hi> at <hi>Banbery.</hi> 1634.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21645:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21645:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONOVRABLE M<hi rend="sup">rs.</hi> FRANCES FIENNES <hi>wife to the Right Worſhipfull</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. IAMES FIENNES <hi>Eſquire</hi> (Sonne and heyre apparent to the Lord Viſcount Say and Seale) and one of the daughters of EDVVARD Viſcount WIMBLETON. <hi>Grace and Peace, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Vertuouſly Noble,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hers nothing in this ſmall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dule preſented to your Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious view but what you know, nor any thing which can be too well learned: the Priests lips are as well to ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and rivet knowledge in the heart, as to tender it to the eare: and the moſt intelligent muſt be, for knowledge, as the Suppliant in the Goſpell was for Faith, and <hi>cry, and ſay with teares, Lord</hi> I know, helpe thou my want of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.
<pb facs="tcp:21645:3"/>
Both must endeavour the procuring ſuch pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticall and ſaving knowledge, by the power whereof the judgement may be rightly enformed, and the will and affections framed for the well ordering of the life and converſation. Your knowne care and ſtudy in this holy practiſe inviteth and emboldneth to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards your Godly acceptance theſe familiar and ever ſeaſonable meditations: the rather for that the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie whoſe late death occaſioned the preſent task, was in her lifetime an afflicted object of your much exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed and voluntary compaſsion, many moneths your chargeable and much tendered patient: too late, for her body, in reſpect of the deſperatenes of her malady (the care being yours, but the cure Gods peculiar) but not too ſoone for her ſoule, which received no ſmall confeſſed phyſick from your counſell, prayers and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample. She lived a daughter of <hi>Iob,</hi> her daies being ſhort and painefull: and dying a daughter of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> in faith and patience, left nothing fitter to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge her debt to you then this part of her fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſolemnity; which therefore I am bold to preſent in her name to your noble deſert. Chriſtians care and paines in doing good to all, eſpecially Faiths hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold, hath ſufficient reward with God: who not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding muſt be glorified by men in the view of
<pb facs="tcp:21645:3"/>
his graces ſhining in his eminent ſervants: which who ſo dare performe with flatterie, let him look un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it: for my part herein ſincerity is conduct, as far as my heart and I be beſt together acquainted. If you, or any for your ſake, reape any price of labour in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this publiſh; I know, God ſhall not want his praiſe.</p>
            <p>Proſper ſtill, with your noble conſort, as your ſoules proſper, to your continuing rich in good workes (the Kings high-way to your kingdome.) Be bleſſed with <hi>Booz</hi> and <hi>Ruth</hi> their bleſsing, <hi>to do worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and be famous:</hi> and let your famous worthines (as it doth) ſhine long through your humility heere, till both your graces be late crowned above in Glory,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours unworthy neighbour ever well-wiſhing you in Chriſt Ieſus ROGER MATTHEVV.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:21645:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21645:4"/>
            <head>THE FLIGHT OF TIME, Diſcerned by the dim ſhadow of <hi>Iobs</hi> Diall, <hi>Iob</hi> 9.25.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>IOB 9.25.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Now my dayes are ſwifter then a Poſt; they flee away, they ſee no good.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words are a part of the ruthfull complaint of afflicted <hi>Iob:</hi> who, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving taken to conſideration Gods ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and power in his afflicting the ſonnes of men, commending the one to be impeachable and no way to be reproved, eſpecially <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. the other to be impregnable and no way to bee reſiſted, particularly <hi>verſ.</hi> 19. drawes towards a concluſion well ſuting with his owne preſent condition, and his friends partiall cenſure of the ſame, <hi>viz.</hi> that the effects of Gods ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and power in trying men by afflictions are not (ſimply) ſound arguments of Gods diſpleaſure: ſith<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ</hi> 22.</note> 
               <hi>the Lord brings to deſtruction both the perfect and the wicked.</hi> So that, whether<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ.</hi> 23.</note> 
               <hi>he pluck away the innocent ſuddenly,</hi> or forbeare &amp; ſeeme to<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ.</hi> 24.</note> 
               <hi>give
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21645:5"/>
the earth,</hi> by way of long poſſeſſion, <hi>to the wicked;</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, ſo <hi>past finding out ſhall his judgements be to us,</hi> (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for tryall or for terrour) that no man ſhall diſcover his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions: yea he covereth <hi>the faces of judges,</hi> ſaith the Text: the beſt diſcerners may as well finde out the furrow of a ſhip in the Sea, or tracke the flight of an Eagle in the ayre, as ſound Gods inſearchables in this kinde; <hi>Iob</hi> deſires to know the mans name and place that dare arrogate the contrary to himſelfe, <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ.</hi> 24.</note> 
               <hi>Who, and where is he?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ſetled, that miſery is no ſound argument of Gods an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, the Patriarke ſticks not (in this verſe read unto you) to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the heavie hand of the Lord upon himſelfe in a threefold degree of that infirmity and wretchedneſſe, whereunto, as all mortality is ſubject, ſo himſelfe was at this preſent ſeverely ſubdued. <hi>Now my dayes are ſwifter then a poſt, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which words note unto us three remarkables of <hi>Iobs</hi> and all humane frailty: Firſt, the ſhortneſſe, Secondly, the ſwift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Thirdly, the ſadneſſe of the ſame.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The ſhortneſſe appeares in the ſmall fragments of it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but Daies. Large extents are meaſured by long dimenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, furlongs, miles, leagues: ſhort by feet, ſpannes, ynches: Daies, yee know, are no long durances, and how can life eeked and pieced out by Daies be of any long continuance?</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſwiftneſſe is diſcovered two waies. Firſt, by a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon to a meſſenger of ſtate, which, notwithſtanding his important haſt, rideth not ſo faſt to his appointed boundary. Secondly, by a ſimilitude (as all metaphors in ſubſtance, are) in a word borrowed from the Fowler, of quicker diſpatch then any horſe or dromedary, <hi>they flee:</hi> amplified by a terme of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing diſtance, <hi>away. Swifter then a poſt, they flee away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The ſadneſſe glimmers forth in the abſence of comfort and proſperity, delivered under the tearme <hi>Good;</hi> and its partly expreſſed by the ſtrongeſt negative, partly confirmed by the ſureſt witneſſe (that of the eye) <hi>they ſee no good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The porch thus opened, lets enter into materials: and firſt to the firſt condition of <hi>Jobs</hi> frailty, and in him, of all mankind in generall, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:21645:5"/>Daies and ſmall pittances of humane life, teaching us this uſefull obſervation,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> That <hi>Mans naturall life is but ſhort,</hi> ſhort daies are all the limmes of mans time, (like a ſhort line con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting but of pricks) the whole body of his time cannot bee long. When <hi>Iacob</hi> had well neere all his yeeres together, he ſummes the totall into a<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 47.9</note> 
               <hi>few daies. David</hi> could gripe all his daies into the compaſſe of a<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 39 5.</note> 
               <hi>Span.</hi> As nature nurtured the heathen in the cutted ſtate of this mortality by a bladder and a bubble, both ſweld, with a puffe, and ſhrunk with a pricke: by a breath whoſe being, or vaniſhing, who can ſay which is ſooner, longer? So grace advertiſeth Chriſtians by moſt ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant compariſons expreſſing their ſhort abode in this<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 146.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>their dust.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle <hi>Iames</hi> would ſcarce vouchſafe it any compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon. <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 4.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Whats your life,</hi> ſaith he? twiting us with our falſe conceit of long life by a holy flout: if it be, ſaith he, of any ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence at all, its but like a vapour that appeareth for a litle time, and then vaniſhes away. What ſaith <hi>David</hi> to our daies? They are ſaith he,<note n="i" place="margin">1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29, 15.</note> 
               <hi>as a ſhadow, and thers no abiding.</hi> And what is <hi>Hezekiahs</hi> opinion? A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſ.</hi> 38.12</note> A ſhepheards tent, of no long ſtay.<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 7.6.</note> A weavers ſhuttle is of no long race:<note n="m" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1</note> a pilgrims taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle ſoone flitted. So vaine a thing is man. How long is wax in melting?<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 22.14</note> So is life in the middeſt of its fortreſſe.</p>
            <p>How durable is the ſtate of<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſ.</hi> 40.7.</note> graſſe?<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 90.5.</note> 
               <hi>We fade away ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly like the graſſe.</hi> Whats a tales grace? Shortneſſe,<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 90.9.</note> 
               <hi>Our yeeres paſſe away as a tale that is told,</hi> a thing gone and paſt. Yea, as if theſe compariſons were yet defective, the Prophet addeth a ſleighter manner of ſimilitude, reſembling mans life to a<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 73.20</note> dreame, and that when its paſt, when a man awaketh; a thing gone before you can collect what it was, and when it was, it was but a thing (or rather a juſt nothing) of meere imagination. But how is it that mans life is thus ſcant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led?</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>
               </label> 1. The principall cauſe is God. <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 39.5.</note> 
               <hi>Thou haſt made my daies as it were a ſpan in length,</hi> ſaith <hi>David.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The provoking cauſe is ſinne. Thats a ſudden waſter. <note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17.</note> 
               <hi>The ſame day thou eateſt, &amp;c. thou ſhalt ſurely die:</hi> God hath
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21645:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſealed it with an oath, <hi>ſurely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The working cauſe, the conſuming effects of ſinne, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and miſery both inward and outward: a houſe of<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 4.19.</note> clay ſo ſtrongly beleagured cannot hold out a long ſiege.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The materiall cauſe,<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 3.19.</note> duſt; he was appointed no long ſtanding whoſe<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 4.19.</note> foundation was laid in duſt.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The procreating cauſe of mankinde neceſſitateth a very ſhort ſtay:<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 14.1.</note> 
               <hi>Man that is borne of a woman hath hut a ſhort time.</hi> If he ſtand to his pedegree it cannot be, that ſhee that hath no fee ſimple nor leaſſe of one houre, can make over any long entale of time to her poſterity.</p>
            <p>The truth of our ſhort abode thus confirmed rather by way of meditation upon a thing much uſefull, then for proofe of a point ſo plaine: what better application ſhall we make then <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> Firſt, by way of checke to rayne backe the outrunners of time in this luxuriant age of dingthrifts of time, waſtfull laviſhers of their ſmall allowance? how many lay about them, as if all their exhibition this way were flong them by talents, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſpend it with like profuſeneſſe as giddie yongſters newly leapt into their lands, ſquandring away by pounds, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in whereof they never knew by pence? ſuch licentious merchants of time trade in every countrey ſo waſtfully, as if they had more time then can be ſpent whiles good; ſo prodigall of daies, moneths, yeares, ſome upon doing nothing, others upon nothing to the purpoſe, many upon whats contrary to what they ſhould doe, till they turne ſtarke bankrupt both for time and grace. Alas its but winde they feed upon when they thinke they fat their ſenſes with a conceit of living as long as ſuch and ſuch a long liver of their progeny, forgetting<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8.</note> 
               <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans</hi> caſe and thouſands more that die before their parents. Fooliſh men, that neither with all their wealth can purchaſe one minute of time, nor with all their ſtrength procure an houre of health, nor with all their wit differ death, much leſſe prevent judgement, yet will never ſeaſon their thoughts with any meditation of weakneſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> death, or judgement. Well, the evill day is never the more diſtant for their putting it off: ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe may come at an inſtant: weakeneſſe will come; death
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21645:6"/>
muſt come: the longer the ſhadow of life ſeemes to be, the neerer their ſun is to ſetting; their glaſſe is running: their houre is at hand when they ſhall make audit before the impartiall judge for all theſe flatteries of themſelves, and for their inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions wherefore they thus deceived themſelves, for all the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties they have omitted, for all the evills they have commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, all the inſtructions they have neglected, all the promiſes they have deſpiſed, all the threatnings they have ſleighted, all the talents of youth, health, ſtrength, wit, &amp;c. they have hidden, and for all the creatures, meanes, and times they have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly abuſed. If any will ſurfet upon hopes of long joy and contentment in licentiouſneſſe, and reſolve (upon that ground) ſtill to turne Gods grace of time yet afforded, and meanes of converſion yet proffered into wantonneſſe of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, let him with his ſweet conceits take this ſorrow ſop amids, that his delights cannot be long and certaine whoſe life is but ſhort and uncertaine. God will ſhortly put an end to his pleaſures and perſon, death groans for him, that ſergeant is within one ſpan of his boſome, his judge begins to laugh as faſt at his deſtruction as he laughes at his inſtructions: time is at hand when his dulleſt ſenſe ſhall feele, to his woe, what his faith now wil not beleeve, that the joyes of this firſt life which he fanſied to be eternall are but few and ſhort, but the miſeries of the ſecond death, which he never dreamt of, ſhall be num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berleſſe, meaſureleſſe, eaſeleſſe, remeadileſſe, and utterly end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> In the ſecond place, this ſerves to reprove a generall fault in all whom the Lord pleaſes to afflict any whit more then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary: it being the guiſe of impatient man to feed his melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly diſtempers and to waſt his ſpirits with meditations upon the length of his afflictions, amongſt whom a yeeres health is ſhorter then they can have while to feele: but a moneths or weeks ſickneſſe is long, and long, and longer then they can beare. If the Lord would glorifie himſelfe in their faith, in their aſſurance of eternall joyes for temporall &amp; ſhort paines, he ſhall not do it: if he will gaine glory by their patience in any tedious durance, he comes to the wrong houſe; they had
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21645:7"/>
rather he loſt his honour then they their eaſe: No, no, benefits be of the ſhorter ſiſe though they laſt moneths and yeares; croſſes of a day muſt be long though life it ſelfe be ſhort.</p>
            <p>What conceive we of thoſe exquiſite tortures which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine the unrepentant idolater, the impenitent blaſphemer, the reſolved offenders of all ſorts in eternall and inextricable wreck and miſery without any eaſe or date? And what intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable impatience to murmure at the ſhorter when we deſerve both theſe? Mend this fault, and do God more honour, the truth more credit, and our ſelves more eaſe by muſing upon mercies, by comparing eternals with temporals, by conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſhortneſſe of thy life, and ſo confeſſe and praiſe the Lord for thy ſhort afflictions, unleſſe thou wilt in fooliſh pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptorineſſe ſay,<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 1 5 9</note> 
               <hi>thou wast the first man that was borne, and waſt made before the hills,</hi> ſufferedſt ever ſince, and reſolveſt to ſuffer for ever after thy departure hence.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, have we but ſhort daies heere to ſpend? What ſhall we doe better then to ſtrive with God in prayer, and our ſelves in practiſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt with God, in commending our requeſts to him in theſe <hi>daies of our fleſh</hi> after our Saviours example; he alone is the meats-man of our daies,<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 7.1.</note> ſetting forth an appointed time to man upon the earth. Pray him in <hi>Davids</hi> words, with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> ſpirit, to<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 85.47</note> 
               <hi>remember how ſhort our time is,</hi> and to remove all hinderances of miſpending, and improve all his owne offred meanes and furtherances for the well-ſpending our ſhort abode heere: and for our ſelves, let's often ſeaſon all outward paſſages with thoughts of our approaching end, mixe them with our marriages, tradings, purchaſes, journeyes, all field en and domeſtick labours, eſpecially with our recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and delights: take heed of engroſſing and griping after more time or temporall things then the Lord affords; bethink how fraile thy ſelfe art, how ſhort thy time, of what manner thy abode: thy daies, as <hi>David</hi> told thee, are but of a<note n="d" place="margin">1 <hi>Cron.</hi> 29.15.</note> pilgrim: thy manſion is not thy home, thy houſe but an Inne; thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily and neighbours are but fellow-paſſengers; if thy corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions within, or Satan and the world without beare thee in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21645:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
hand with enough layed up for many yeeres, give them all the lie with the tongue of this Text: and be ſure that though thou muſt converſe in the world, yet to keepe thy ſelfe free from the<note n="e" place="margin">2 <hi>Pet</hi> 1.4</note> corruptions of the world, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſtiles them, Its hard,<note place="margin">Bernard.</note> but much diſcourſe of temporall things will gnaw the conſcience, as the rivers fret their bancks: but holy circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection and moderation will eaſe that difficulty: the blinde want, though verſed all in the earth, ſtill preſerves its velvet coat faire from the filth of the earth; thou haſt thy eyes about thee, nor needſt thou delve ſo deepe: ſo converſe thou in earthly matters that thy conſcience be not defiled, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware thou ſuffer not the earth ſo to bury thy ſoule before thy body die, but that thou maiſt uſe thy eyes to diſcrie death pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping over thy ſhoulder whiles thou lookeſt upon thy worldly matters, or (if farther off) to ken it in its full gallop and flight to overtake thee, and thats the ſecond part of this taske, <hi>viz.</hi> the ſwiftneſſe of mans life in the <hi>Post,</hi> haſt or rather flying of the ſame. <hi>My daies are ſwifter then a Poſt: they flee away:</hi> from whence who cannot ſpell forth this leſſon.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label>
               <hi>Mans life is ſwift as well as ſhort.</hi> Our daies ſeeme wing-footed: <hi>Iob</hi> ſeemes doubtfull whether they run or flee. The ſwifteſt rider is too ſlow to make expreſſure; the fowles wings beſt Emblems forth lifes quick diſpatch: and that when it makes to the prey: and that of the<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 9.26.</note> Eagle, not only for ſwift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe but ſtrength, which no humane obſtacle of either youth, wit, wealth, honour, or phyſick can ſtay or hinder from its ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed goale. The proverb drops too ſhort that ſaith <hi>Time and Tide ſtay not:</hi> Tides creepe on but ſlowly and have their interſtices, ſtay ſomwhat when they have their ſtints, chalenge their returnes: Time is neither ſo, nor ſo. The Prophet ſpeakes more home. Our time, yea the<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 90.80.</note> ſtrength of it, is ſoone cut off, <hi>we flee,</hi> yea <hi>we flee away,</hi> and that without either<note n="h" place="margin">1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.15.</note> abiding ſaith <hi>David,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 7.9.</note> returning as <hi>Iob</hi> hath it.</p>
            <p>The Holy Ghoſt is ample for compariſons, as before: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling mans ſliding ſtate to things ever upon the rode of haſt. To a<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſ</hi> 40 7.</note> floure that fades apace. To<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 12.14</note> water that runs apace. To a<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 9.26</note> ſhip that ſailes apace. To a Poſt and an Eagle,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21645:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
as ye ſee, that rides and flees apace. Theres no keeping pace with time but upon the wings of the<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 7.7.</note> Winde that whirles apace.</p>
            <p>But how comes this to paſſe, that man in his beſt eſtate though in honour, is thus altogether a flying vanity and abideth not?</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>
               </label> 1. If natures reaſon may carry it, the ſubject and founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of time runs (as it were) all on wheeles: the heavenly Orbs, (of ſwifter motion then of any flying bullet from the ſtrongeſt Ordenance) whirle the times about: amongſt which, the unceſſant circuits of the Sunne and Moone are appointed (by him that<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſ.</hi> 40.22.</note> ſits upon the circle of the earth, and meteth out Heaven by the ſpan) to meaſure forth theſe earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly yeeres,<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ.</hi> 12.</note> moneths, and dayes, till all time be ſwallowed up into eternity and theſe heavens be no more: How then can our daies be ſlow?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Doe not ſinne, and ſinners make quicke worke in the world? How ſpeedily do men breake into it? Even<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 58.3.</note> from the wombe; With what eager purſuit doe men follow ſinne? Even (like <hi>Iehues</hi> furious march) ſwiftly:<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 6.18</note> their feet are ſwift in running to miſchiefe; ſome faſter, ſome ſlower, all too faſt. How would wickedneſſe tyrannize might it in this heat have while to roote and ſpread, and ſeed according to the luſt of ſinfull men? And who ſhall hinder ſwift ſinners from bringing upon themſelves ſwift deſtruction?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Neither is experience ſo ſenſeleſſe of the reaſon (<hi>a parte poſt,</hi> as they ſay) by a touch of after-wit, that perceives every minute of time ſo flight that it prevents the quickeſt catch, gives the heedfulleſt attention the ſlip, and out-ſtrips the ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieſt chaſe. The time to come is but only in conceit, the time is fled in inſtants: who can ſay of any time preſent, now it is, ſith it out-runs thy thought?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> This ſhreds off the ſuperfluous deſires of many men, male-contented with their preſent ſtates: who, like infants after youth, and youth after riper age, are ever liquering after fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture times. Oh, were ſuch a quarter day come, or ſuch a yeere or time expired, they were made. Why? what hadſt got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21645:8"/>
by this catch if thou couldſt finger ſome thred of time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Sun can ſpin it? Firſt thou ſhouldſt get but a wilde foule, a ſhadow, a puft, whoſe haſty vaniſhing would more vexe, then its approach did pleaſe. Secondly is the thing, for which thou ſo over-reacheſt, good or evill? If thou haſt ſuch a greedy worme under thy tongue for that which is evill, that like<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 85.30</note> 
               <hi>Eſau</hi> for the pottage, or <hi>Elies</hi> ſonnes for the fleſh, thou wilt needs have it.<note n="t" place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.16.</note> Now, or (in a ſort) wilt take it by force: hearken what the next verſe telleth thee,<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ.</hi> 17.</note> Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thy ſinne is very great before the Lord. But admit the thing bee good for which thou wouldſt ſo faine ſteale upon the time to come; aſſure thy ſelfe, it would come ſo raw (as <hi>Iacobs</hi> abortive bleſſing did) that thou wouldſt not reliſh the bitterneſſe that would accompany the taſt of it, for pluck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Gods appointed ſeaſon (which onely ripeneth all) to thy britle luſts: beſides, ſo weake (generally) doe ſuch men prove in the well-ordering of time ſo over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, that, when its come, they are as unable to uſe it as to hold it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, this aggravates the vexation of a worſe ſort of men, whoſe anxiety is moſt, for that their youth ſlips away ſo faſt, and their age comes on ſo cloſſe, that they feare leaſt they ſhall not have all their ſports in, all their cups in, all their pleaſures and profits in time enough. Oh, that they could realize that<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 49.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> inward thought of ſome that their houſes ſhall continue for ever! Oh, that they could cauſe the ſhadow of their lifes diall to ſtand ſtill two or three <hi>Methuſelaes</hi> ages, or goe backe to <hi>Adams</hi> time and take them along to eternity of paſtime! No, no, time is irrevocable for the paſt, unſtayable for the preſent: their ſhadow is declining, their glaſſe running, their ſunne ſetting apace: Gods purſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant death is more then in poſte-haſt, even like the Eagle towards its prey: their pleaſures ſwift as the Sunne, and flie apace; Gods wrath ſwift and comes apace: ſwift death, ſwift damnation treads upon the heeles of all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent haſtening of evill workes, and putting off of the evill day.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:21645:9"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> How much better to haſten with the time to a profitable inſtruction to redeeme the time paſt, and improve the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. If miſ-ſpending of the time paſt be ſufficient, as that <note n="y" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.3</note> Apoſtle ſaith; what ſhall wee better ſet about then the <note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.16</note> redeeming it being ſuffered by us (for want of due care and watchfulneſſe) to be carried captive by Satan to the ſervitude of ſinne: labour we by prayer and repentance and new obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, to make our evill daies good daies, and ſo to reſcue and recover our time into its liberty againe: And for our preſent allowance of time, if<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 12.12.</note> Sathan ſo much the more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtirs himſelfe for evill by how much ſhorter time he knoweth he hath: how much more ſhould we buſtle for good, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how many hundred times ſhorter ours is in theſe cabbins of clay? O, then be we thriftie of our time being ſhort and precipitate alſo: and the faſter we diſcerne our Sun to ſet, the more haſt like honeſt labourers and wiſe travellers lets make to diſpatch our worke and journey: goe wee along with the day, and let a day have a daies worke, a weeke a weekes, &amp;c. and proceed as faſt in ſervice as our daies in paſſage, ſpend this ſpeciall intruſtment no faſter then it comes in: its beſt wiſedome to take our daies before us, not neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting if young to <hi>remember our Creator</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccle.</hi> 12.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>in the daies of our youth.</hi> It cannot be denied but that its poſſible for an old ſinner to repent and turne: howbeit, he is likelieſt to bee ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſt, as in wealth, ſo in grace, that begins betimes: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides how unlikely that a man ſhould be able to catch repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance at pleaſure in age and ſickneſſe, who hath beaten backe the Lords proffered grace in youth and health; the Lord is likely to bee well requited for all his favours, to have all the blade and floure of a mans age caſt to his vtter foes, and the refuſe and ſtumps reſerved for him: and its very likely wee ſhall fight a goodly field when for very impotency wee are ready to be turned forth of th'campe.</p>
            <p>Oh, then learne better, while we have ſtrength, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory to number our daies more wiſely, and with <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eſpatian</hi> the Heathen prince plucke our ſelves by the eare for every loſt day, and redeeme the next.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:21645:9"/>What a feaſt will it be to a mans conſcience, when hee hath ſpent according to his exhibition of time; and having a price put into his<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 17.16.</note> hand, hath not wanted a heart to uſe it? Reſolve upon it, howſoever thou haſt failed in thy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer beginnings this way, thy conſtant proceedings in well imploying thy ſhort time will quit the coſt, and bring in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in ſickneſſe, diſtreſſe, temptation, death when world of preferments, profits, and paſtimes ſhall ſtand but as vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations before thy conſcience.</p>
            <p>As that mans ſtate upon his deaths couch is miſerable whoſe conſcience (then moſt of all) will embolden diſputes againſt him, what he hath done with time, why he melted the fat of it to ennimble the wheeles of his luſts for quicker diſpatch of ſinne: objecteth why done ſo much evill ſo little good: and now after ſo much ſinne contracted, ſo little grace glea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, what will now become of him, when his time and hee are both at laſt caſt? So, on the contrary, how happie hee, whoſe walke can ſhew him, and his conſcience witneſſe with him, that ever ſince he knew what time meant, and percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved how faſt it paſſed, hath beene no looſer by the uſe of good opportunities, but as he felt them ſlipping away, ſo he layed on better holt, caſting how to imploy the ſmalleſt mites of time ſome about his honeſt vocation, other ſome in hearing, reading, meditating, conferring, and eſpecially praying: ſome for his own particular, ſome for his family, ſome for others, all for the working and atchieving ſome true good for himſelfe and as many as he can: with what courage ſhall he look temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and death in th'face, and, after all his painefull daies works in courſes of piety, ſhut up the windowes of his life to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a bliſſefull reſt in happy immortality?</p>
            <p>The ſecond comfort belongs to all Gods children under any affliction: their daies paſſe apace, their ſorrowes cannot ſtay long; paine ſhal not long vexe, foes ſhall perſecute but a while: The<note n="c" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17.</note> Apoſtle ſummes up the afflictions of this life into a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. What ſpeake we of thoſe nibbling croſſes of the body? The kill-cow of all, ſinne ſhall make no long havocke in their ſoules, not long bane their peace, nor ſhipwrack their ſecurity:
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21645:10"/>
pluck they up their hearts, theſe ſtormes will over, theſe ſad daies will have a night of joy: the time flies towards us when we ſhall have no time nor heart to grieve the Lord, no time to provoke him to grieve us: the<note n="d" place="margin">1 <hi>Sam</hi> 31 4.</note> ſword that pierced <hi>Sauls</hi> breſt was nothing to the weapon wherewith our Lord Ieſus Chriſt hath wounded Satans head: his ſpirits, and ſins vitals are blee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding forth apace: meane time, all that Satan and ſin can do to us, is but to make us more heedfull and watchfull in our waies; all that death can do is but to turne the key and open the dore before us to a heavenly manſion. Comfort one another in theſe words, that the time hies apace, even ſwifter then a Poſt, that Satan and ſin ſhall have no more to do with us; heaven miſſeth us as much as we earne for it, God will ſhortly call for us, the Angels ſhall carry us, Chriſt Ieſus ſhall intertaine us, his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſhall welcome us, his<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ</hi> 17.15</note> image ſhall ſatisfie us. Let this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigate the ſadneſſe of humane life, (eſpecially of the Saints) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Third and laſt conſideration from the Text. <hi>They ſee no good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The word <hi>good</hi> is of eaſie explication by noting how the word evill (its contrary) is in Scripture diſtinguiſhed. There's one evill in the roote, as it were, partaking of that<note n="f" place="margin">1 <hi>Iob.</hi> 5.18.</note> Evill one Satan and thats the evill of ſin, in relation whereunto its ſaid of wicked times,<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.16.</note> 
               <hi>the daies are evill.</hi> Theres another evill in the branches, and thats the effect and fruit of ſin, <hi>viz.</hi> miſery; in which reſpect daies of ſorrow are termed<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12 1.</note> 
               <hi>Evill daies.</hi> So (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the rule of Oppoſites) the word <hi>Good</hi> hath a double ſenſe drawne upon it: Firſt as it participateth of the <hi>Good</hi> God in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe: ſo Godly works are ſtiled <note n="i" place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.18.</note> good works: Secondly, as it partakes of Gods bounty in the proſperity &amp; comfort of the creature: in which reſpect<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 34.12</note> proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous daies are called Good, and this is the proper ſenſe of the word in this Text; <hi>Iobs</hi> daies ſaw no Good, that is, much miſery: much loſſe in ſtate, much feare in his children, much paine in his body, much diſcouragement from his friends, much horrour in his ſoule: all which as <hi>Iob</hi> ſuffered by way of triall, ſo all are ſufferable by demerit: which takes us out a <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>3</label> Third profitable, though hard, leſſon, <hi>viz. Our ſhort ſwift time is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21645:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to great and ſore affliction.</hi> Short and ſweet were ſome miti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, but our daies are as ſowre as ſhort. Swift and pleaſant were ſome qualification, but they are knotty and ſad as well as ſwift. All our daies are not faire, long, ſommer daies, but many gloomy, ſhort, winter nippy daies among. <hi>Iobs</hi> whole ſtory to the laſt Chapter, what iſt but a ruthfull Martyrologie of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſtory well concurred with his confeſſion, that his daies were<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.7</note> 
               <hi>few and evill:</hi> The Patriarke <hi>David</hi> had his ſtint this way, being exerciſed with<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 71.20</note> great and ſore troubles: and if the righteous are recompenſed upon earth with troubles for number<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 34.19</note> many, for meaſure<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 2.13.</note> great,<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 11.31.</note> how much more, ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> the wicked and the ſinner? Speake experience; of what condition is the vaniſhing vapour of our life? When we have made a hard ſcape from ſtifling in the wombe, whats in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy, but a brak of diſcontents? whats child-hood, but a ſchoole of reſtraint from without, a very bridewell of frowardneſſe within? Whats youth, but a pitcht field of paſſions and diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers? Whats age, but a meere hoſpitall of infirmities? Our whole life worſe than a tragedy, (for that begins with ſome mixture of delight) wherein the firſt act is crying; the ſecond grieving: groaning is the laſt Cataſtrophe. No marvaile then if <hi>Iob</hi> calculate mans time to be not only ſhort, but<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 14.1.</note> 
               <hi>full of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> For why? The Lord hath ſo appointed it, as <hi>David</hi> and <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah</hi> upon their ſick beds acknowledge. God hath layed this heavie yoke upon all the ſons of <hi>Adam</hi> either for puniſhment or for tryall, and thers no eſcaping a thing decreed. Were it any way avoideable, wiſdome might diſcry ſome prevention. Were theſe ſtormes only upon the land or upon the ſea alone, the advantage of eaſe might be taken by the place; were they only without dores, one might houſe himſelfe within: but be he where he can be, he cannot avoid what he is borne to. Man is borne ſaith <hi>Iob</hi> to trouble,<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 5.7.</note> as the ſparks flie upwards.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> Affliction is ſins native brood; if this hang on, the other will not fall off: its ſin that makes mans time narrow as a well for breadth, deepe as hell for bitternes, why els doth<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 18.4.</note> 
               <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Ionah</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ionah</hi> 2.2</note> complaine of helliſh ſorrowes? whoſoever therefore
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21645:11"/>
followes ſin becomes afflictions prey, neither have the law; and the Prophets noted any other chace for afflictions hunting but only the ſinner. If no man can ſay, he hath clenſed his heart from ſin, no man ſhall be able to rid his ſoule or body from ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. Truth is, ſin hath no fitter meanes wherby to execute its own ends then this. What aimeth ſin at? Death and deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. What breaks and battereth downe more forcibly then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction? Man made mortall muſt downe, iniquity is the axe, miſeries the ordinary ſeverall ſtrokes that lay the ſinner along.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Do all ſuffer or deſerve to feele theſe ſtormes that paſſe the ſea of this mortality? Then this muſt firſt reſolve what to truſt to heere. This world is not a meadow full of flowers, but a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe of brakes and briars; now, this affliction catches at us; now, an other, at ſins ſute, areſts us; now a foe dogges us, anon a ſicknes laies us up: waking, ſleeping, dreaming: cares, atches, feares, craſineſſes and diſtempers, as thick as<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 1.14.16.17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>Iobs</hi> ill meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, haunt us; Dreame of what eaſe and comfort thou wilt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thy ſtate and condition ſo and ſo altered to thy mind, how thou ſhalt live as merrily as the day is long to (as your proverbe runs) after thy yoke-fellow obtained to thy minde, after all thy reverſions outlived, all thy purchaſes compaſſed, preferments atchieved, children placed; deceive not thy ſelfe: even after all thoſe, thou wilt flote upon a ſea of ſin, and therfore no leſſe then a ſea of waves, and rocks and ſhelves and ſtormes and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats ſhall annoy and continually endanger thee. Art Gods tree? thou muſt be pruned; art Gods tilth? thou muſt be bowelled up with plow and harrow, els thou wilt be fruitleſſe: art Gods childe, chaſtiſed thou muſt be or graceles. Art Gods enemy? he notes thy prancks, and is providing ſowre ſauce for thy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant morſels: His hand is taking holt of vengeance, he is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſhing his<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 32 41.</note> glittering ſword, that his arrowes may drink the blood, &amp; his ſword eate the fleſh of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that hate him. Finally, be thou good or bad, ſet not to thy heart any deſcant of pleaſant ditty, whiles all the tune of thy life runs upon diſcords of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; if any comforts appeare, they are but as the gleames of a March day beaten with ſtormes as faſt as they glimmer forth; and therefore as thou doſt not unſlate thy houſe when the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21645:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſhowre is paſt, but keepeſt it to award another: ſo, put not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way faith and patience and watchfulneſſe at the departure of any croſſe, but taking a ſhort farwell, reſerve thy ſelfe to wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the ſame againe or worſe, ſith this is not the haven but the Ocean.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Neither may we omit one duty in reſpect of our decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed friend, ſorrow indeed becomes us conſidering what ſtrange havock ſin and death make of creatures ſo excellent: howbeit in reſpect of the deceaſed, what ſtrange matter is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallen them? What more uſuall, more naturall then for a man to die. Yeſterday, ſaith the Philoſopher, I ſaw a pitcher break, and to day I ſee a man die: the matter is no more ſtrange thats befallen thy wife, thy childe, thy brother, thy friend: he is but gone the way of all the earth; But whats the alteration, what hath the<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 23.14</note> party let fall to th'ground? any more but nerves and ſinews, as the verſe hath it? ought els but a weak, craſy, putre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying body there to be perfumed againſt the reſurrection? Whats the loſſe but a loſſe of much ſinne, a loſſe of many ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, of more dangers: and why ſhould theſe diviſions be ſuch thoughts of heart? What would we deſire more in our friends behalfe then the Lord hath done for them in their hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py tranſlation if they lived and died in him? Would we pull them back againe and hold tugge<note n="y" place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18 33.</note> as <hi>David</hi> for his <hi>Abſolom</hi> againſt the Lord himſelfe for them? No. What then? would you have them ſmart longer, ſuffer longer? Would you have the moth of anguiſh fret the garment of their fleſh longer, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction grind their very bones longer? Would you have Satans blowes to aſſaile them ſtill, ſins poyſon to endanger them for ever? Mend this fault of over-grieving at friends departure: ſo mourne, as <hi>Abraham</hi> for deceaſed <hi>Sarah,</hi> and to riſe from our friends corps, as<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 23.3</note> he did from hers. View we our owne condition in the glaſſe of their mortality; theres no long time of diviſion twixt them and us: we muſt ſhortly cut over the ſame ferry and meet them on the other ſide of th'ſhore: deaths boat was not appointed to carry all at once: the ferry not made to land all at one tide: ſtay the returne of the water for our turne: and taking but a ſhort leave of the deceaſed, joying at
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21645:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
their ſafe arivall, uſing ſurvivers better, preparing to part with all, pray for a proſperous gale. In the meane, husband we out uncertaine, ſhort, and ſwift time well: diſpatch our works and willes againſt the tides returne: and ſith we have many talents committed to our traffique, and barks of our owne to furniſh, lets play the wiſe merchants, not to load our little veſſels with all ordinary lumber and trumpery which every ſeller ſaith is good (more like to ſhipwrack us by the way then pleaſure us at the ſhore) but take up that which <hi>David</hi> preferres before<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 19.10.</note> much fine gold, bart for that which<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 28.18.</note> corall &amp; pearles are not to be named with; nor<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 3.15</note> Rubies or any other deſirables are to be compared unto: buy the<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro</hi> 23.23.</note> Truth: purchaſe that hid trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure commended by our<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 13 44.</note> Maſter, if the ſelling of all we have will reach it, and ſo ballace our ſmall veſſels with the choyſeſt wares, that an ever bleſſed thirſt may welcome our arivall. There our faith will leave us, not our charity: let that grace work by this vertue now, for the beſt improving of al comforts, for whats our wit or ſtate to procure, continue, uſe, or miſſe the leaſt of them? and for the bearing of all croſſes of this life, for whats our ſtrength or naturall armour to prevent, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, remove, or award the eaſieſt of them? Lay holt of the promiſes by faith in our Redeemers life,<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 19.25</note> as <hi>Iob,</hi> in his extrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities; wreſtle it out by prayer, as<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 32 26</note> 
               <hi>Iacob,</hi> in his anxieties: commit our ſelves to our<note n="h" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.18.</note> faithfull Creator, get<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4</note> comfort in his word,<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.17.</note> joy in his ſpirit, and<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1.</note> Prince Michael to ſtand up for us amongſt the children of his people, and then al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it bee true,<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16.33.</note> 
               <hi>In the world yee ſhall have tribulation,</hi> yet it is as true, <hi>Christ hath overcome the world, in him yee ſhall have peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
